Noah Weeth Feinstein, curriculum vitae

225 North Mills Street Madison, Wisconsin 53706-1795 Phone 1-650-387-8414 Fax 1-608-263-9992 nfeinstein@wisc.edu

Research interests

I am an interdisciplinary scholar who studies the dynamic and multi-facetted relationship between science and public, and the many possible roles education might play in shaping that relationship. Much of my research is rooted in Science and Technology Studies (STS) and responds to that field's longstanding fascination with science "at large" in society. In particular, I work to understand how, when, and in what contexts science matters to non-scientists. I approach the problem at both the human scale, studying how engagement with science emerges from the demands of everyday life, and at the scale of institutions and social trends, studying how shifts in scientific practice influence the relationship between science and public. Specific projects have focused on: engagement with science among parents of recently diagnosed autistic children, equity-oriented programming in museums and science centers, doctor-patient interaction around internet health information, and the science café movement. I also maintain an active research program in education for sustainability.

Education

2008	PhD in Science Education, Stanford University
2006	MS in Biological Sciences, Stanford University
1998	AB in Biology, Harvard University

Title of doctoral thesis: Coming to Grips with Autism: Parents engaging with science

Positions held

2010 –	Assistant Professor, Community & Environmental Sociology – University of Wisconsin-
	Madison
2008 –	Assistant Professor, Curriculum & Instruction – University of Wisconsin-Madison
2008-2010	Assistant Professor, Agronomy – University of Wisconsin-Madison
2004-2008	Research/Teaching Assistant – Stanford University School of Education
2002-2004	Research Assistant – Stanford Education Assessment Lab
2001-2002	Assistant Project Evaluator – The Exploratorium, San Francisco, CA
1999-2001	Senior Research Assistant – Sociometrics Corporation, Los Altos, CA
1997	Research Intern (summer) – National Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution,
	Washington, DC
1996	Research Intern (summer) – Marine Biological Institution, Woods Hole, MA

Special honors and awards

2008	New Scholars Fellowship for Best Multi-Authored Paper, Canadian Society for Studies in
	Education
2007	Lieberman Graduate Fellowship, Stanford University
2006	Selected for Doctoral Consortium, International Conference of the Learning Sciences
2002	Stanford Graduate Fellowship, Stanford University

Research and publication

(* indicates peer review)

Research and other scholarly papers

- 1. * Feinstein, N., Læssøe, J., Blum, N., and Chambers, D. (in press). Challenging the premises of international policy reviews: An introduction to the review symposium. *Environmental Education Research*.
- 2. * Feinstein, N., Jacobi, P., and Lotz-Sisitka, H. (in press). When does a nation-level analysis make sense? ESD and educational governance in Brazil, South Africa, and the United States. *Environmental Education Research.*
- 3. * Læssøe, J., Feinstein, N., and Blum, N. (in press). Environmental Education Policy Research: Challenges and ways research might cope with them. *Environmental Education Research*.
- 4. * Feinstein, N. (2012). Making Sense of Autism: Progressive engagement with science among parents of young, recently diagnosed autistic children. *Public Understanding of Science*. Advance online publication.
- 5. * Kleinman, D., Feinstein, N., and Downey, G. (2012). Beyond commercialization: Science, higher education, and the culture of neoliberalism. *Science and Education*. Advance online publication.
- 6. Feinstein, N., and Carlton, G. (2012). Education for sustainability in the US K-12 educational system, in R. McKeown and V. Nolet (Eds.), *Schooling for Sustainable Development in Canada and the United States*, pp 37-51. New York: Springer.
- 7. * Halverson, R., Feinstein, N., and Meshoulam, D. (2011). School Leadership for Science Education. Research in Science Education: Vol. 5, G. DeBoer (Ed.), *The Role of Public Policy in K-12 Science Education*. Greenwich, CT: Information Age Publishing.
- 8. * Feinstein, N. (2011). Salvaging Science Literacy. Science Education 95(1), 168–185.
- 9. * Feinstein, N., Fielding, K., Udvari-Sollner, A., and Joshi, S.V., (2009). The Supporting Alliance in Child and Adolescent Treatment: Enhancing Collaboration between Therapists, Parents and Teachers. *American Journal of Psychotherapy*, *63*(4), 319-344.
- 10. Feinstein, N. (2009) Prepared for What? Why teaching "everyday science" makes sense. *Phi Delta Kappan*, 90(10), 762-766.
- 11. * Card, J.J., Benner, T., Shields, J.P., and Feinstein, N. (2001). The HIV/AIDS Prevention Program Archive: a collection of promising prevention programs-in-a-box. *AIDS Education and Prevention* 13(1), 1-28
- 12. * Feinstein, N., and Cairns, S. (1998). Learning from the Collector: A survey of azooxanthellate corals affixed by Xenophora (Gastrapoda: Xenophoridae), with an analysis and discussion of attachment patterns. *The Nautilus* 112(3), 73-83
- 13. * Feinstein, N., Yelenik, Y., Maclelland, J., and Valiela, I. (1996). Growth Rates of Ribbed Mussels in Six Estuaries Subject to Different Nitrogen Loads. *Biological Bulletin* 191, 327-328
- 14. * Yelenik, S., Maclelland, J., Feinstein, N., and Valiela, I. (1996). Changes in N and C Stable Isotope Signatures of Particulate Organic Matter and Ribbed Mussels in Estuaries Subject to Different Nutrient Loading. *Biological Bulletin* 191, 329-330

Research publications in progress

- 1. Feinstein, N., Allen, S., and Jenkins, E. (in review). Outside the pipeline: Re-imagining science education for non-scientists.
- 2. Feinstein, N., and Meshoulam, D. (in preparation). Equity in informal science learning: An interview study of fifteen leading institutions.

3. Feinstein, N., Ellis, A., Newman, A., Hess, D., Juzwik, M., Osborne, J. (in preparation). Finding common ground: Pedagogies of discussion and argumentation across the disciplines.

Policy reports, book reviews, and practitioner publications

- 1. Feinstein, N. (2011). Book Review: Diversity and Equity in Science Education: Research, Policy and Practice. *Science Education* 95(3), 571-573
- 2. Læssøe, J., Schnack, K., Breiting, S., Rolls, S., Feinstein, N., Goh, K.C., and Jensen, B.B. (2009). Climate Change and Sustainable Development: The Response from Education. Copenhagen, Denmark: International Alliance for Leading Education Institutes. (http://www.intlalliance.org/alliance.html)
- 3. Feinstein, N. (2009). Education for Sustainable Development in the United States of America. Copenhagen, Denmark: International Alliance for Leading Education Institutes. (http://www.dpu.dk/edusud/documents/)
- 4. Feinstein, N., and Davis, R. (2006). *Hawaiian Ecosystems in Flux: A research-based environmental science unit for grades 7-8.* Stanford, CA: Woods Institute for the Environment.
- 5. Feinstein, N., Card, J.J., Shields, J.P., Benner, T., and Hamner, K. (eds). (2001). *Case Studies in Effective HIV/AIDS Prevention*. Los Altos, CA: Sociometrics Corporation.
- 6. Bunch, M., Feinstein, N, & Prentice, B. (eds.). (2001). *Gender and AIDS Almanac*. Geneva, CH: UNAIDS.
- 7. Feinstein, N., Card, J.J., Spreng, B. & Codispoti, F. (2001). Teacher Housing in the Palo Alto Unified School District: Problems and solutions. Palo Alto, CA: Sociometrics Corporation & Palo Alto Foundation for Education.

Research Support

- 1. PI: Testing the competent outsider hypothesis in public engagement with science. The University of Wisconsin-Madison Graduate School Fall Research Competition. (8/2013 6/2014) \$31,050.
- 2. Co-PI: Understanding Innovative Science: The Case of the Wisconsin Institutes for Discovery. The National Science Foundation, STS/SciSIP programs. (8/2012 7/2014) \$371,271.
- 3. Co-PI: A Mixed-Methods Study of Clinician Empathy in the Context of Patient Self-Advocacy. The University of Wisconsin-Madison Graduate School Fall Research Competition. (8/2011 6/2012) \$34,045.
- Co-PI: CALS-Milwaukee Collaboration for Agriscience and Urban Sustainability Education. Reilly Baldwin Wisconsin Idea Endowment, Morgridge Center for Public Service. (9/2010 – 6/2013) \$140.974.
- 5. Co-PI: Understanding Innovative Science An Investigation of the Wisconsin Institutes of Discovery. The University of Wisconsin-Madison Graduate School Fall Research Competition. (6/2010 6/2011) \$71,872.
- 6. Co-PI: STS and Science Education proposal for integrating STS scholars into university courses. Holtz Center for Science and Technology Studies, University of Wisconsin-Madison (6/2010 12/2010) \$5000.
- 7. PI: Public Engagement with Science at the Bleeding Edge of Climate Change How Wisconsin Farmers Conceptualize and Respond to the Challenges of Farming in a Warmer and Less Predictable World. The University of Wisconsin-Madison Graduate School Fall Research Competition. (8/2009 7/2010) \$37,610, The University of Wisconsin-Madison Graduate School. (2009-10)
- 8. PI: Spencer Foundation Research Training Grant. Spencer Foundation. (9/2007 6/2008) \$6500.

Research proposals under review

- 1. PI: What makes a competent outsider? Understanding high health literacy among the chronically ill and their caretakers. National Institutes of Health. (\$180,045).
- 2. Co-PI: Online health-information seeking: effects on the doctor-patient relationship. Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality. (\$95,908).
- 3. Co-PI: Physician empathy and patient self-advocacy a mixed-methods study. Arnold P. Gold Foundation for Medical Humanism. (\$24,163)

List of Presentations (invited and conference)

- **Invited Presentation:** "Science literacy and the competent outsider in higher education." Bard College/HHMI Colloquium on Science Literacy. March 7, 2013; Annandale-on-Hudson, NY.
- Invited Presentation: Closing forum "How do we make Madison a Living Laboratory for Sustainability & Resilience?" Badger Bioneers conference, December 13, 2012; Madison, WI.
- Invited Presentation: "Sustainability and the curriculum in higher education." University of Wisconsin Systemwide Meeting on Sustainability. November 2, 2012; LaCrosse, WI.
- Invited Presentation: "Who and when is private? Exploring the edges of public-ness at an interdisciplinary research institute." NSF Science of Science and Innovation Policy (SciSIP) conference. September 21, 2012; Washington, DC.
- "Responding to the internet-savvy patient: A mixed methods study of physician empathy and patient selfadvocacy." Presentation accepted for the 2013 annual meeting of the American Educational Research Association, San Francisco, CA.
- Discussant: "Redefining school science to promote public engagement with science." Panel presentation accepted for the 2013 annual meeting of the American Educational Research Association, San Francisco, CA.
- Session organizer and chair: "Science Education for the Competent Outsider: What we already know and do." Session for the 2012 annual meeting of the American Educational Research Association. April 16, 2012; Vancouver, BC, Canada.
- "Culture Contact and the Competent Outsider How should we think about public engagement with science?"
 Presentation for the History of Science Brown Bag seminar series, University of Wisconsin. February 24, 2012;
 Madison, WI.
- Invited Presentation: "Creating Meaningful and Useful Exams." Presentation at the National Pesticide Applicator Certification and Training Conference. August 11, 2011; Portland, OR.
- Invited presentation: "Science Education for the Competent Outsider: Lessons from Public Engagement with Science." Presentation at the Joint DFG-NSF conference on Public Understanding and Public Engagement with Science. June 30, 2011: New York, NY.
- Session organizer and chair: "Balancing epistemology and empowerment: Discussion, argument, and dialog across the disciplines." Session for the 2011 annual meeting of the American Educational Research Association. April 10, 2011; New Orleans, LA.
- Invited presentation: "The Trading Zone: Optimizing time with your doctor and building a strong supporting alliance." Presentation at the 4th Annual Autism Spectrum Disorders Update conference. April 2, 2011; Stanford. CA.
- Discussant: "Emotional Disability and the Logic of Lobotomy." Panel presentation at Boundaries of Disability: an Interdisciplinary Symposium. February 25, 2011; Madison, WI.
- "Climate Change and Education: Where do we begin?" Atmospheric and Oceanic Sciences Symposium, University of Wisconsin-Madison. November 1, 2010; Madison, WI.
- Invited presentation: "Education for Sustainable Development in the United States." Presentation to US-Japan Fulbright Teacher Exchange program, Institute of International Education, April 26, 2010 (repeated in updated form in 2011, 2012).
- "Equity in Informal Science Learning: Reconciling Research and Practice." Paper presented at the 2010 annual meeting of the National Association for Research in Science Teaching, March 22, 2010; Philadelphia, PA.
- Session Organizer and Chair: "Diversity, Equity and Informal Science Learning: New Data and New Directions."
 Session for the 2010 annual meeting of the American Educational Research Association, May 3, 2010; Denver, CO.

- Session Organizer and Chair: "Tracing the Influence of Science and Technology Studies on Science Education Research." Session presented at the 2010 annual meeting of the American Educational Research Association, May 1, 2010; Denver, CO.
- "Trading zones, boundary objects and public engagement with science." Paper presented at the 2009 annual meeting of the Society for the Social Studies of Science, October 31, 2009; Washington, D.C.
- Invited international presentation: "Governance and Progress in American Education for Sustainable Development." Paper presented at the 2009 annual meeting of the International Alliance of Leading Education Institutes, August 19, 2009; Seoul, Republic of Korea.
- "Trading zones, boundary objects and public engagement with science." Holtz Center for Science and Technology Studies, April 30, 2009; Madison, WI.
- "Coming to grips with autism: parents engaging with science." Paper presented at the 2009 annual meeting of the American Educational Research Association, April 16, 2009; San Diego, CA.
- "What parents of autistic children know (and what they discover) about the nature of science." Paper presented at the 2009 annual meeting of the American Educational Research Association, April 15, 2009; San Diego, CA.
- "Autism, meaning and action." Paper presented at the 2007 annual meeting of the Society for the Social Studies of Science, October 12, 2007; Montreal, QC, Canada.
- Session Organizer and Chair: "What Does it Mean to You? Making, Merging, and Judging Meaning across Socio-cultural Contexts." Session for the 2007 annual meeting of the Society for the Social Studies of Science, October 12, 2007; Montreal, Canada.
- "Using what we know: Public engagement with climate change." Paper presented at the 2007 Science and Technology in Society Graduate Student Conference, April 1, 2007; Washington, D.C.
- "Silenced by science? Parents of autistic children finding their voices." Paper presented at the 2006 annual meeting of the Society for the Social Studies of Science, November 2, 2006; Vancouver, BC, Canada.
- Session Organizer and Chair: "The silent treatment: how patients, parents and practitioners are selectively silenced in mental health encounters." Session for the 2006 Annual Meeting of the Society for the Social Studies of Science, November 2, 2006; Vancouver, BC, Canada.
- "Coming to grips with autism: parents engaging with science." Paper presented at the doctoral consortium of the 2006 International Conference of the Learning Sciences, June 27, 2006; Bloomington, IN.
- "What scientists get from science outreach in a museum setting." Poster presented at the 2005 annual meeting of the American Educational Research Association, April 13, 2005; Montreal, Canada.

Teaching

Public Engagement with Science

Science in Daily Life (Graduate Seminar)

Science and Technology Studies

- STS and Science Education (Graduate Seminar)
- Interdisciplinarity and the Modern Research University (Graduate Seminar)

Agriscience Education

- Foundations of Agricultural and Environmental Science Education (Undergraduate Intro Course)
- Signature Pedagogies in Agricultural and Environmental Science (Undergraduate Seminar)
- Program Planning in Agriscience Education (Undergraduate Practicum)

Science Education

- Research Methods in Mathematics and Science Education (Graduate Methods Course)
- General Seminar Research in Science Education (Graduate Seminar)

Environmental and Sustainability Education

- Sustainability, Democracy, and Education (Undergraduate Intro Course)
- Scholarship and Practice in Environmental and Sustainability Education (Graduate Seminar)

Advising and mentoring

Since arriving at UW-Madison in August, 2008, I have served as major advisor for five doctoral students (three in Curriculum and Instruction plus two multidisciplinary students). The first of my doctoral advisees expects to finish in June 2013. I have also served as advisor for five masters-level students (two in Curriculum and Instruction plus three in Agroecology). Two of these have successfully completed their degrees. In addition, I have served on over a dozen MS and PhD committees, including multiple doctoral committees in the department of Life Science Communication.

Service

Professional

- Editorial Board, Science Education (A Wiley International Journal). 2008-2011
- Book Review Co-Editor, Science Education (A Wiley International Journal). 2008-2010
- Peer review: Science, Public Understanding of Science, Science Education, Educational Psychologist, Journal of the Learning Sciences, Environmental Education Research, Comparative Education Research, The Sociological Quarterly
- National Science Foundation proposal reviewer and panelist: Informal Science Education; Science, Technology, and Society.
- Advisory Board: "Deliberating the New Energy Economy" (PI Phadke; NSF). 2010-11
- Advisory Board: "SYNERGIES: Understanding and Connecting STEM Learning in the Community" (PI Falk; Noyce Foundation). 2011-13
- Advisory Board: New Models of Science Literacy for Undergraduate Education (PI Keesing; Howard Hughes Medical Institute's Precollege and Undergraduate Science Education Program). 2012-2014.

University Service

- Faculty Senator UW-Madison Faculty Senate (2009-present)
- Personnel Committee Department of Curriculum & Instruction (2012-present)
- Graduate Programs Committee Department of Curriculum & Instruction (2008-2012)
- Undergraduate Education Committee Department of Community & Environmental Sociology (2012-present)
- Steering Committee Agroecology Program (2010-2011)
- Admissions Committee Agroecology Program (2010-2011)
- Curriculum Committee Department of Agronomy (2008-2010)
- Coordinator UW-Madison Program in Agriscience Teacher Education (2008-2010)
- Affiliate Holtz Center for Science and Technology Studies, University of Wisconsin-Madison (2008-present)
- Affiliate Center for Climatic Research, University of Wisconsin-Madision (2011-present)